Guide to the Jane Hoffer Photographs 1975-2012, 2020, 2022 PR 312
New-York Historical Society
Jane Hoffer photographs
1975-2012, 2020, 2022
New-York Historical Society
Hoffer, Jane
PR 312
1.5 Linear feet in two boxes.
16.84 Gigabytes (642 digital files)
Photographs, contact sheets, CDs, and photobooks by Jane Hoffer, documenting female members of the New York Police Department (1975–1979); the Boys' Choir of Harlem (1980–1985); celebrities from the fields of activism, the arts, business, education, journalism, and politics (circa 1983–2010); and Willets Point, Queens (2020).
Arrangement
The collection is organized in four series:
Series I. "On the Beat," 1975-1979, 2011-2012
Series II. "Boys' Choir of Harlem," 1980-1985, 2011
Series III. "Celebrity," circa 1983-2010
Series IV. "Willet's Point, Queens," 2020
Biographical note
Canada native Jane Hoffer is a New York City-based photographer with more than forty years of freelance experience. Hoffer attended McGill University where she started in painting and ended her graduate career with a dissertation on photographic essays. She received further training at the School of Visual Arts, the New School, the International Center of Photography, and Columbia University, from which she holds an advanced degree in art. Hoffer's primary professional work has been for non-profit organizations, including the Boys' Choir of Harlem and Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts. In addition to her commercial work, Hoffer has pursued many artistic projects that have been exhibited throughout the city in both group and solo shows. She is currently a member of Professional Women Photographers, the West Side Artists Coalition, and the National Association of Photoshop Professionals. For further information visit the photographer's website: www.janehoffer.com.
Access Restrictions
For more information on making arrangements to consult the boxed photographic prints, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Digital files can be made available online for viewing only. To arrange to receive a link to the desired digital files, contact reference@nyhistory.org.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Jane Hoffer donated the material in Series I in 2012. In 2018 she supplied additional copies of the interview transcripts in Series I (Box 1, Folder 24), plus all of the material in Series II and Series III (accession no. PPAC.2018.018). Ms. Hoffer donated the Willets Point images (Series IV) in August 2022.
Related Material at Other Institutions
The New York City Police Museum also holds a collection of Jane Hoffer's photographs of policewomen.
Scope and Contents
The photographs in this collection stem from four distinct documentation projects by Jane Hoffer: "On the Beat" (1975–1979); "Boys' Choir of Harlem" (1980–1985); "Celebrity" (circa 1983–2010); and "Willet's Point" (2020).
"On the Beat" (1975–1979) documents some of the first women police officers out on patrol in New York City. President Lyndon Johnson's Crime Commission in 1967 recommended sweeping changes to law enforcement training and hiring practices and called for "new kinds of people" in police forces: college graduates, women, minorities, and skilled civilians. More and more women became patrol officers and moved into supervisory positions like station supervisor and detective. Further studies, like the Kerner Commission's 1968 "Report of the National Advisory Commission on Civil Disorders," and psychologist and Ford Foundation director Catherine Miller's 1972 study, "Women in Policing," contributed to the changing attitude toward women stepping out from behind the desk to take on more active policing duties. Policewomen faced fierce resistance from people outside their departments, as well as resentment from their fellow officers.
Hoffer began the project in the 1970s. She was then teaching photography at John Jay College of Criminal Justice, and the photography collective to which she belonged, Women Photographers of New York, began a series of projects on working women. A colleague introduced her to Sergeant Joan Pearson, who then acquainted her with other female officers who were willing to be interviewed and photographed. Fascinated by the emerging roles of women in police work, Hoffer photographed officers, sergeants, and auxiliaries in precinct houses, their patrol cars, and at the firing range. She also conducted extensive interviews of her subjects. The process continued for four years.
The photographs were exhibited at the SoHo Photo Gallery (1980), the Wall Gallery at the John Jay College of Criminal Justice (1989), and the New York City Police Museum (2011), where the exhibit was called "On the Beat 1975–1979: Women in the NYPD." The work was also issued as a self-published photobook, On the Beat 1975–1979, which contains selections from the interviews as well as photographs.
An impromptu request to shoot a Boys' Choir of Harlem concert led to Hoffer's first professional job: photographing the choir at venues around New York City (Carnegie Hall, City College, Gracie Mansion, and Liberty Island), throughout the United States, and on a trip to Jamaica. Hoffer also accompanied the choir to its summer camp in Kent, Connecticut, where she captured the singers rehearsing, studying, fishing, and swimming. In 2011 Hoffer issued her images in a self-published photobook, The Boys' Choir of Harlem 1980–1985. The Boys' Choir of Harlem was founded in 1968 by Dr. Walter Turnbull (1944–2007). The group folded shortly after its final performance in 2007.
The photographs in Jane Hoffer's self-published Celebrity were taken between about 1983 and 2010 at New York City locations such as the Apollo Theater, Columbia University, the New York Academy of Science, Hunter College, Radio City Music Hall, and the City College of New York. Hoffer's subjects include activists, artists, authors, photographers, businessmen, philanthropists, scientists, educators, journalists, performers, actors, dancers, directors, musicians, political figures, and religious leaders, all of whom are identified in the container list, below (Series III, Box 1, Folder 29).
Jane Hoffer's website provides the following statement regarding her Willets Point photographs: "Since the 1930's, Willet's Point has been the home for a community of automotive businesses that service, repair and salvage vehicles. The area has been scheduled for gentrification and garages have been reduced to about half the original number. Despite the deplorable neglect of the neighborhood - no street lights or sewers, potholes, mud and water everywhere - there is no shortage of customers who drive there in droves knowing that the work force is skilled and the parts they need will definitely be available."
Boys' choirs.; Celebrities; Policewomen -- New York (State) -- New York; Contact sheets.; Photobooks.; Photographs.; Digital images.; Digital file formats.; Compact discs.; Willets Point (New York, N.Y.); Boys' Choir of Harlem; New York (N.Y.). Police Department
- Series I. "On the Beat", 1975-1979, 2011-2012, 2022; 2 Gigabytes (224 files) +; .3 Linear feet (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains photographs and other material relating to "On the Beat 1975-1979: Women in the NYPD," an exhibition of Hoffer's photographs of some of the first female NYPD officers on the job. The photographs are arranged in categories originally determined by the photographer. For descriptions of her subjects, see the container list below.
  There are 131 gelatin silver photographs in Series I (105 are 5x7-inch prints; 25 are 11x14-inch prints), as well as 8 contact sheets with 160 images, some labeled "Women Partners," for which there are no prints in the present collection.
  Series I also includes a CD of images and interview texts, and the photographer's self-published photobook On the Beat 1975–1979, which reproduces photos and selections from the interviews, all of which were performed with the women represented in the collection. Note that some of the photographs present in the collection do not appear in the book; and, conversely, some of the images in the book are not represented in the collection.
  A booklet, which includes some of Hoffer's photos, was added to the collection by Hoffer in 2022.
  - Auxiliaries, circa 1977, [undated] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-2)
    Two mounted officers, Susan Cohen and Susan Cooke, pictured riding and caring for their horses.
  - Collins, circa 1975, 1978, [undated] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3-4)
    Sergeant Barbara Collins, depicted in her precinct, in dress blues, processing suspects, and on patrol.
  - Decoys, circa 1976-1977, 1978, [undated] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5-6)
    Officers disguised as vulnerable citizens to act as plants to lure muggers. The photographs are mostly of Officer Rita Kaplowitz, a member of the street crime unit, and show her being disguised as an older woman, at the station, and speaking to senior citizens in costume.
  - Hartmann, [undated] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7-8)
    Officer Mary Hartmann shown assisting on EMT calls, turning out at roll call, and on patrol in dress blues.
  - Knedlehans, 1978-1979, [undated] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9-10)
    Officer Helen Knedlehans, an emergency service officer and instructor, depicted teaching first aid and using the jaws of life on a car.
  - Pearson, circa 1975, [undated] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11-12)
    Sergeant Joan Pearson shown in the precinct house, on late night emergency calls, at the precinct cells, and out on patrol doing "community relations."
  - Stanton, circa 1976, [undated] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13-14)
    Sergeant Marcia Stanton shown in the precinct house, answering disturbance calls, and doing her make up.
  - Shaughnessy, 1976, 1978, [undated] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15-16)
    Officer Peggy O'Shaughnessy shown at the shooting range, on patrol, at the station, helping on an EMT call, and in front of a burned out building.
  - Doran, [undated] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
    Officer Val Doran photographed in the locker room.
  - Walker, 1975, 1978, [undated] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18-19)
    Officer Walker, whose first name and rank were unknown to the photographer, shown on patrol and answering disturbance calls.
  - Wilson, circa 1975, circa 1977, 1978, [undated] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20-21)
    Ann Wilson, a physical instructor at the Police Academy, shown teaching self defense to men and women, working with police recruits, and instructing physical training.
  - "On the Beat" contact sheets, [1975-1979] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    8 sheets with 160 thumbnail images.
  - "On the Beat" CD, [1975-1979] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 23)
    Conditions Governing Access
    The digital files have been transferred off the CD to N-YHS servers. The CD is for back-up purposes only and is restricted from use except by internal processing staff.
  - "On the Beat" digital files, [1975-1979] (Digitalfolder PR 312)
    Digital images of the contact sheets. The digital files have been transferred off the CD to N-YHS servers. A file manifest is available upon request.
    The digital files can be made available online for viewing only. To arrange to receive a link to the desired digital files, contact the Reference Librarian at reference@nyhistory.org.
  - "On the Beat" interview transcripts and exhibit card, [1975-1979], 2011 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 24)
  - On the Beat 1975-1979. Photographs by Jane Hoffer [photobook], 2012 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 25A)
  - "Women Officers of the NYPD" booklet, 2022 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 25B)
    NYPD publication re: history of women on the police force. Gift of Jane Hoffer, 2022.
- Series II. "Boys' Choir of Harlem", 1980-1985, 2011; 1.2 Gigabytes (113 files) +; .1 Linear feet (3 folders)
  In the foreword to her self-published photobook The Boys' Choir of Harlem 1980-1985, Hoffer notes that the Choir (founded 1968; folded 2007) was her first client. An impromptu shoot of a concert led to her photographing the singers at such New York City venues as Carnegie Hall, City College, Gracie Mansion, and Liberty Island, as well as on tour in the U.S. and on a trip to Jamaica. Series II contains contact sheets of Hoffer's photographs, a CD holding digital versions of the same, and a copy of her book.
  - "Boys' Choir of Harlem" contact sheets, [1980-1985] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 26)
    5 sheets with 92 thumbnail images.
  - "Boys' Choir of Harlem" CD, 1980-1985 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 27)
  - "Boys' Choir of Harlem" digital files, 1980-1985 (Digitalfolder PR 312)
  - The Boys' Choir of Harlem 1980-1985. Photographs by Jane Hoffer [photobook], 2011 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 28)
- Series III. "Celebrity", circa 1983-2010; 2 Gigabytes (224 files) +; .1 Linear feet (2 folders)
  Jane Hoffer photographed celebrities between about 1983 and 2010 at such New York City venues as the Apollo Theater, Columbia University, the New York Academy of Science, Hunter College, Radio City Music Hall, and the City College of New York. Series III contains contact sheets of Hoffer's "Celebrity" photographs, a CD holding digital versions of the same, and a copy of her self-published photobook reproducing the images.
  - "Celebrity" contact sheets, [circa 1983-2010] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 29)
    11 sheets with 213 thumbnail images of
    Activists
    Arthur Ashe, Marian Wright Edelman, Coretta Scott King, Andrei Sakharov, Elie Wiesel
    Artists, Authors, Photographers
    Meridith Lynn Auld (Mrs. Tom Brokaw), Art Buchwald, Christo and Jeanne-Claude, Mario Vargas Llosa, Frank McCourt, Gordon Parks, Ann Patchett, Gary Trudeau, Dr. Ruth Westheimer, Tom Wolfe
    Businessmen, philanthropists, scientists
    Anthony Fauci, Eugene Lang, Richard "Dick" Parsons, David Rockefeller
    Educators
    Geoffrey Canada, Maxine Greene, Michele Meyers (president, Sarah Lawrence College)
    Journalists
    Jane Alexander, Tom Brokaw, Walter Cronkite, Sam Donaldson, Amy Goodman, Jeff Greenfield, Bryant Gumbel, Carol Jenkins, Peter Jennings, Robert MacNeil, Jane Pauley, Dan Rather, Cokie Roberts, Tim Russert, Morley Safer, Joel Siegel, Liz Smith, Mike Wallace, Barbara Walters
    Performers (actors, dancers, directors, musicians)
    Tony Bennett, Boys' Choir of Harlem, Cab Calloway, Kitty Carlisle, Ossie Davis, Ruby Dee, Spike Lee, Mitch Miller, Arthur Penn, Pearl Primus, Elisabeth Röhm, Ron Silver, Dawn Upshaw
    Political figures
    Hugh Carey, Bill Clinton, Mario Cuomo, David Dinkins, Geraldine Ferraro, Rudy Giuliani, Mark Green, Ed Koch, C. Everett Koop, Colin Powell, Charles Rangel, Chuck Schumer, Donna Shalala, Alan Simpson, Eliot Spitzer, Andrew Stein, Percy Sutton, Andrew Young
    Religious leaders
    Calvin O. Butts III, Edward Cardinal Egan
  - "Celebrity" CD, circa 1983-2010 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 30)
  - "Celebrity" digital images, circa 1983-2010 (Digitalfolder PR 312)
  - Celebrity. Photos by Jane Hoffer [photobook], [circa 2010] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 31)
- Series IV. "Willet's Point, Queens", 2020; 11.7 Gigabytes (142 files) +; 1 Linear feet in 1 flat box
  The series holds 142 digital images taken in Willets Point, Queens, by Jane Hoffer in 2020. 76 of these are the same image in multiple digital formats, including some in Hoffer's Photoshop versions. 28 of the images were also printed by Hoffer; 5 in color, 23 in black and white. The prints are 17x11 inches. The images are of automotive service, repair, and salvage yards, the cars and other objects that fill the yards, the employees that work in the yards, and other individuals. In two of the prints, the New York Mets' home stadium, Citifield, can be seen in the near distance just past the yards.
  A sampling of the images in the colletion can be found on Jane Hoffer's website at https://www.janehoffer.com/portfolio/willets-point
  - Willets Point Prints, 2020 (Box 2)
    In addition to the 28 photographic prints, this box holds the two CDs and the USB thumb drive with the digital images. The CDs and thumb drive are for back-up purposes only and are restricted from use except by internal processing staff.
  - Willets Point Digital Images, 2020 (Digitalfolder PR 312)
    Digital images of the prints as well as additional images. The digital files have been transferred off a USB drive to N-YHS servers. A file manifest is available upon request.